Dr Nasir Idrees

Health Systems Specialist at Technical Resource Facility (TRF), Islamabad, Pakistan

drnasiridrees@gmail.com

Summary

I am a Public Health Specialist having exposure to, and experience of working multi-sectorally for over twenty two years, with a primary focus on development and implementation of policies, strategies, reforms, projects and programs (conceptualized and developed Sindh and revamped Khyber Pakhtunkhwa Health Sector Reforms Units operational documents, Emergency Response –Rescue 1122 program for Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, Rural Emergency Services Ambulance Initiative – RESAI - for 10 districts of Pakistan through PAIMAN - USAID), innovative models & Public Private Partnership models (Accelerated Educational Initiative model for meeting the LHW and CMW matriculation prequalification criteria of induction, PPP service delivery models for the Primary Health Care-PHC- and Contracting In & out models for outsourcing PHC services in Khyber Pakhtunkhwa and Punjab, Private Providers performance incentives model for collection of Health Information System data across all provinces of Pakistan through PAIMAN - USAID). I have the honor of conceptualizing, developing, designing and implementing the reform agenda of the Country (Pakistan) in various capacities including work in areas of Public Health Policy, development of Strategies, Planning, Reforms, Health System Strengthening and Financial Management (Medium Term Budgetary Framework and developing Risk Mitigation Plan for Fiduciary Risk Assessments conducted in Khyber Pakhtunkhwa and Punjab) in health sector. This involvement spreads across Public and Private Sector and also includes management and implementation of different Programs/Projects. The experience ranges over all Provinces and Special areas in Pakistan including Khyber Pakhtunkhwa, Punjab, Sindh, Balochistan, Azad Jammu & Kashmir, Gilgit Baltistan and Federally Administered Tribal Areas (FATA).

Experience

Health Systems Specialist TRF Islamabad at Technical Resource Facility (TRF), Islamabad, Pakistan June 2011 - Present (2 years 2 months)

This is a senior advisory level position and entails strategic advice to the Federal and the Provincial Governments of Pakistan vis-à-vis the broader health sector. The position provides overall technical guidance to all Policy, Strategy, Financial Management and Health Systems Strengthening related Technical Assistance both to the National and the Provincial Health Departments provided through funding by DFID and AusAID. It encompasses frequent interaction with the Federal and the Provincial Governments and the development partners/donors at a strategic level. Over the period have been able to steer the development of the Health Sector Strategies of the six provinces of Pakistan with a team of consultants and conceptualized, developed terms of reference and provided oversight and technical guidance and review to all the teams; I am also involved in developing the work plan for the project and am currently working on the organizational restructuring of the Health Departments in a devolved setup, giving support in the development of Medium Term Budgetary Framework Support (MTBF), development of the Minimum Health Services Standards and Minimum Health Services Package for the public sector facilities, developing a Risk Management Plan based

on the Fiduciary Risk Assessment conducted earlier by DFID, conceptualizing Contracting In/Contracting Out for outsourcing the Health Service Delivery in the districts both in Punjab and Khyber Pakhtunkhwa in addition to multiple other TAs.

Team Leader -Development of PC-I for the Establishment of Health Sector Reforms Unit (HSRU) Sindh at USAID

April 2011 - June 2011 (3 months)

Development of PC-I for the establishment of Health Policy & Reforms Unit Government of Sindh along with proposal for interim arrangements till PC-I approval, Short term Consultancy (TAUH USAID)

Team Leader; Evaluation of the USAID funded Improved Child Health Project FATA at USAID March 2011 - June 2011 (4 months)

Team Leader for the End Term Evaluation of a Large 97 Million USD USAID Health Project implemented in the Federally Administered Tribal Areas (FATA) of Pakistan. As a result of this Evaluation the Project was extended for another two years.

Team Leader -Evaluation of the USAID funded Improved Child Health Project (ICHP) FATA at USAID

March 2011 - April 2011 (2 months)

Team Leader; Evaluation of the USAID funded Improved Child Health Project FATA (ICHP) Short term Consultancy.

National Technical Advisor Policy, Planning and Coordination at Oxford Policy Management October 2010 - February 2011 (5 months)

Policy advice to the Government of Khyber Pakhtunkhwa on institutional, Governance and Financial Reforms. advising the Government of Khyber Pakhtunkhwa on linking the Policy perspectives with Planning. finalized the Comprehensive Development Strategy (CDS) for the Khyber Pakhtunkhwa Government, Finalized the Agriculture Department Reforms Statement for the Agriculture Department for Khyber Pakhtunkhwa Government.

National Manager Private Sector Initiatives, USAID funded JSI PAIMAN Project at John Snow, Inc. (JSI)

October 2008 - September 2010 (2 years)

Conceptualized and developed Concept Paper for the Public Private Partnership (PPP) service delivery models, designed and implemented the models.

- 1. Community Emergency Transport System (CEAS) an innovative community partnered model for addressing the access issue and targetting the second and the third delay in labor.
- 2. Partnership with Health Care Providers in Private Sector (MNCH): Partnerships were developed with 300 private health care providers across Pakistan and they were asked to submit data on reporting forms developed and handed over to them with performance based incentives.
- 3. Medical Helpline (for MNCH interventions): Established a toll-free and multilingual number to provide health information which is accessible Pakistan-wide, a pioneer innovation in Pakistan.

4. Linking Health & Educational Sector: To meet with the pressing need for improving the health status of the remote and rural communities and to partner/strengthen the MNCH Program and the National Program for FP & PHC two accelerated educational initiatives one for the MNCH and the other for the LHW Program were started as a tripartite Public Private Partnership for the remote districts of Khyber Pakhtunkhwa and Balochistan.

Chief of Health Sector Reforms Unit, Health Department Government of Khyber Pakhtunkhwa at Government of Khyber Pakhtunkhwa - Pakistan

May 2007 - October 2008 (1 year 6 months)

Led the Policy and Reforms Agenda of the Health Sector of Khyber Pakhtunkhwa Province of Pakistan. This included giving the main policy advise to the Secretary Health and to the Government of Khyber Pakhtunkhwa's line departments on matters related to health sector.

Deputy Chief/Acting Chief Health Sector Reforms Unit (HSRU), Health Department Khyber Pakhtunkhwa at Health Department Khyber Pakhtunkhwa

April 2006 - May 2007 (1 year 2 months)

Policy advise on the technical aspects of the health sector reforms, planning, budgeting, service delivery, and program implementation and handling all matters of Government with the Development Partners. All coordination with the Federal Ministries on technical aspects.

Coordinator Foreign - Donor Assistance - Health Sector Reforms Unit (HSRU) at Department of Health, Government of Khyber Pakhtunkhwa

March 2005 - April 2006 (1 year 2 months)

Coordinating as the main interface between Donors and Development Partners on behalf of the Government of Khyber Pakhtunkhwa on health sector affairs. Key Position.

Deputy Provincial Coordinator, National Program for Family Planning and Primary Health Care [LHW at Department of Health, Government of Khyber Pakhtunkhwa

September 2005 - March 2006 (7 months)

Managing the Lady Health Workers (LHWs) matters of the Provincial Program Implementation Unit.

Program Manager ARI/CDD Control Program Khyber Pakhtunkhwa at Department of Health Government of Khyber Pakhtunkhwa

January 2002 - February 2004 (2 years 2 months)

Looking after all technical and managerial affairs of the DoH Khyber Pakhtunkhwa on Acute Respiratory Infections & Communicable Disease Control (ARI &CDC).

Assistant Director; Public Health at Directorate General of Health Services Khyber Pakhtunkhwa January 2002 - February 2004 (2 years 2 months)

All Public Health Matters both Technical and Managerial were tackled through this position based in the DG Health Office Peshawar - Khyber Pakhtunkhwa - Pakistan

Deputy Medical Superintendent at City Hospital, Peshawar

December 2000 - January 2002 (1 year 2 months)

Hospital management position.

Multiple Managerial, Technical and Clinical position at Department of Health Khyber Pakhtunkhwa - Pakistan

September 1990 - January 2000 (9 years 5 months)

Junior Consultant undergoing fellowship training in medicine.

Registrar Medical Unit Khyber Teaching Hospital Peshawar (January 1994 to March 1996).

Provincial Coordinator (Government Counterpart): 1993—1994. Integrated Drug Demand Reduction Project (IDDRP) UNDP.

Provincial Coordinator (Govt. Counterpart): (1992 to 1994) Pakistan Child Survival Project Khyber Pakhtunkhwa.

Assistant Director Rehabilitation (Drug Abuse) Khyber Pakhtunkhwa (March 1991 to January 1994).

Medical Officer in Rural and Urban primary, secondary and tertiary health care facilities and hospitals (1993 to 1999)

House Surgeon and House Physician in Khyber Teaching Hospital Peshawar, Pakistan (November 1988-October 1989).

Languages

English

Skills & Expertise

Health and Social Sector Reform and Restructuring Governance and institutional Reforms Policy and Planning

Financial management Reforms

- Fully versed with the Government systems and procedures; provincial health ref
- Health systems research both qualitative and quantitative including proposal &
- In depth understanding of health systems of Pakistan and its working environme Monitoring, Evaluation and supervision

Describerant of Training Metables

- Development of Training Materials
- Public policy development and its translation into strategic and implementatio
- Public health/Social sector program management and implementation (design, pla
- Fully versed with budget support mechanisms and Medium Term Budgetary Framewor
- Thorough understanding of public health accounts and their functioning
- Good facilitation, communication and presentation skills including excellent c
- Thorough understanding of bilateral and

multilateral donor systems including g

- Networking and partnership development
- Extensive experience in staff management including development and implementat
- Well versed in procurement and logistic systems of donors and government.
- Strong leadership qualities
- Thorough understanding of public-private, private-private and public-public pa
- In-depth understanding of the public sector development programs including fun
- Development of reform concepts & project development/implementation, research
- Proposal development and report writing
- Monitoring and Evaluation framework development
- Advocacy and Social Mobilization
- Health systems development and strengthening
- Public health programs –design, development and implementation
- Public Finance Management
- Budget planning and execution including financial forecasting.
- Grant Management and oversight

Healthcare

Health Economics

Public Health

Health Policy

Healthcare Management

Hospitals

Policy

Epidemiology

Program Evaluation

Global Health

Policy Analysis

Clinical Research

Program Management

Education

Provincial Health Services Academy Khyber Pakhtunkhwa

Masters in Public Health MPH, Public Health, 2002 - 2004

Grade: A

Khyber Medical College Peshawar

Bachelor of Medicine, Bachelor of Surgery (MBBS), Medicine, 1983 - 1988

Grade: A

Interests

Writing Poetry and Playing Golf

Dr Nasir Idrees

Health Systems Specialist at Technical Resource Facility (TRF), Islamabad, Pakistan

drnasiridrees@gmail.com



Contact Dr Nasir on LinkedIn